Guide to the George L. Fox Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Levi Fox papers
1874-1930
MS 975
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Outgoing letters, draft of a Ph.D. dissertation, a diary, clippings, printed matter, and miscellaneous papers. The outgoing letters consist of a letter book about George L. Fox's investments in Florida orange groves in the 1880s and a series of drafts of letters to various newspapers on Irish and English politics (1917-1925). The diary records his travels in England and Europe in 1921 and 1923.
Fox, George L. (George Levi), 1852-1931
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of George L. Fox, 1931.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection brings together various items pertaining to George Levi Fox. Three bound volumes are included, one a letterbook concerned with Fox's investments in Florida orange groves in the 1880s, the second a diary for 1921 and 1923 containing scattered entries about travels to Europe and England, and the third a thesis submitted for the Ph.D. at Yale University (no degree was conferred).
The bulk of the collection consists of writings by and about Fox. Included are a number of typescript and manuscript drafts of essays, addresses, and letters to the editor on politics and education, newspaper clippings and other printed matter largely on English and Irish politics and on education, and several articles about Fox's activities on behalf of the Labour Party in England and against Irish Independence. There are, finally, several miscellaneous items of memorabilia and printed matter.
These papers were the gift to Yale University of the estate of George L. Fox in 1931.
Biographical / Historical
George Levi Fox, B.A. 1874.
Born November 16, 1852, in New Haven, Conn.
Died August 6, 1931, in New Haven, Conn.
Father, Levi Goodell Fox, an engineer; son of Joseph Kneeland and Sally (Gray) Fox, of Hadley, Mass. Mother, Elizabeth Hamlin (Bodfish) Fox; daughter of Simeon and Elizabeth (Hamlin) Bodfish, of Windsor, Conn.
Hopkins Grammar School. Entered Yale with the Class of 1873, but left during the first term on account of ill health; reentered with the Class of 1874; first prize in English composition Freshman year; second Berkeley Premium Sophomore year; dissertation appointment Junior and Senior years; speaker at Commencement; an editor of Yale Courant; member Gamma Nu, Phi Theta Psi, and Psi Upsilon.
Taught the classics at General Russell's Collegiate and Commercial Institute, New Haven, 1874-75; engaged in private tutoring in New Haven 1875-77; studied in Yale Graduate School 1874-77 and Yale School of Law 1878-79 (LL.B. 1879); admitted to bar of New Haven County; senior teacher in Latin and Greek at Hillhouse High School, New Haven, 1877-1885; M.A. 1885; rector of Hopkins Grammar School 1885-1901; head of Fox Tutoring School, New Haven, 1885-1926; lecturer on municipal administration at Yale 1895-1900; gave course of twelve lectures on the Great Public Schools of England before Lowell Institute, Boston; had also lectured widely on same subject and against Sinn Feinism; assisted in Liberal Budget Election campaign in England 1909; took part in campaign against the House of Lords 1910; member Connecticut Commission on Arbitration and Mediation 1917-1920; member Committee of Seven of American Historical Association on the teaching of history 1896-98 and contributed to its Report; author: The Study of Politics (1885) and of numerous critical pamphlets on Prussianized Germany, Sinn Feiners, and Panama Canal; contributed to the Nation, Journal of Education (London), London Spectator, Political Science Quarterly, Yale Review, Yale Alumni Weekly, Proceedings of American Political Science Association (of which a member) (1906), School and Society, New York World, and Springfield Republican; member Connecticut Civil Service Reform Association, and Center Church (Congregational), New Haven.
Unmarried.
Death due to acute myocardial failure and diabetes mellitus. Buried in Evergreen Cemetery, New Haven. Survived by two nephews, one of whom is Edward L. Fox, '93 S. By the terms of his will Yale was made one of the residuary legatees, the bequest to be used for scholarships to be known as the George L. Fox Scholarships; his library also was given to Yale University with the provision that duplicates should be made available to the New Haven Public Library.
(Taken from Yale University Obituary Record ).
Florida -- Industry; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1910-1936; Diaries; Educators; Fox, George L. (George Levi), 1852-1931
- Inventory
  - Letterbook relating to orange groves in Florida, 1883-1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - London diary, 1921, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Writings
    - "Charitable Endowments among the Romans up to the Time of Constantine," a thesis submitted for the Ph.D. at Yale (but no degree was awarded), 1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Draft article for Political Science Quarterly, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Draft letter to the New York Times, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Testimony before the Committee on Education of the Connecticut General Assembly, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Draft letter to the Literary Review, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Draft letter to the Spectator, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Draft letter to the Journal-Courier, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Brief of an address to the [New Haven] Board of Finance with regard to the Budget of the Board of Education", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Criminal Immorality of Germany", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "American Opinion on Irish Affairs", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Draft letter to the Journal-Courier, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Clippings and printed matter, 1893-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 7 - 18)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1874-1923 (Box 1, Folder 19)